<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the chappel of St. James's, before His Highness the Prince of Orange, the 23d of December, 1688 by Gilbert Burnet.</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10152315</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10152315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1378:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the chappel of St. James's, before His Highness the Prince of Orange, the 23d of December, 1688 by Gilbert Burnet.</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Reprinted at Edinburgh by John Reid,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXVIII, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44659:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44659:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED In the Chappel of <hi>St. James</hi>'s, Before His HIGHNESS the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> the 23d. of <hi>December,</hi> 1688.</p>
            <p>By GILBERT BURNET D. D. Chaplain to His HIGHNESS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by His Highneſs's Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Re-Printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by <hi>John Reid,</hi> Anno DOM. 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:44659:2"/>
            <p>Licenſed and Entred according to Order,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44659:2"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSALM cxviii. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</bibl>
                  <p>It is the Lord's doing, and it was marvellous in our Eyes.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>THings do ſometimes ſpeake, and times call aloud; and as all Men are before hand with me, in the choice of this Text, at leaſt in applying it to the preſent time, ſo that amaſing Concurrence of Providences, which have conſpired to hatch and bring forth, and perfect this extraordinary Revolution, would lead one very naturally to uſe theſe words, even tho we had no ſuch Verſe in Scripture; for we have before us a Work, that ſeems to our ſelves a Dream, and that will appear to Poſterity a Fiction: a Work about which Providence has watched in ſo pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar a manner, that a Mind muſt be far gone into Atheiſm, that can reſiſt ſo full a conviction as this offers us in favour of that Truth. And if a threed of happy ſteps on the one hand, and of miſtaken ones on the other, can upon any occaſion be made an Argument, we have it here in its utmoſt force.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>the Lord's doing,</hi> not as the Heavens and Earth, as the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Day and Night, and the whole Chain of Second Cauſes are his Work: The whole Springs of Nature are wound up by him, ſo that all things are in ſome ſort his doing: He gives alſo a ſecret Direction to all ſecond Cauſes to accompliſh his Eternal Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. He knows all the foldings of our Hearts, and the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of our Natures ſo well, that without putting us under a force, he can bring about whatſoever pleaſes him. He alſo on ſome great occaſions does Violence to Nature, and puts her out of her Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel in thoſe extraordinary Productions that are called Miracles. But beſides all theſe, there are times in which the great Governour of Heaven and Earth will convince the World, that he is not an unconcerned Spectator of Human Affairs: But becauſe Men are apt to be ſo partial to themſelves, and to their own Opinions, as to look on every favourable Accident as a ſmile from Heaven, and that Sanguine People are as ready on the one hand to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves God's Favourites, and the ſpecial Objects of his Care, as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Men on the other, in the fourneſs of thought that oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them, conſtrue every thing that ſucceeds not according to their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44659:3"/>Wiſhes, as the effect of ſome croſs Aſpect on them; it is neceſſary to find the Temper between flattering our ſelves too much, and the charging our ſelves too ſeverely; and to examine Providence by ſuch equal and juſt meaſures, that we may neither put too much on the common courſe of Second Cauſes, nor aſcribe too much to ſuch Specialties as our Partialties may incline us to imagine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in our favours: for becauſe we are always kind to our ſelves, we are very apt to believe that Heaven is ſo too. But to come cloſer;</p>
            <p n="1">1. All ſignal and eminent things are by the common Phraſe of Scripture aſcribed to God; and therefore every Event that is great in its ſelf, and may become yet much greater in its Conſequences, ought to be imputed to an immediate Hand of Heaven: ſome that have judged that a ſpecial Direction of all things was too great a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction to his Divine Beeing, &amp; a trouble unworthy of it, have yet thought that its care extended to great matters. If then this may be laid down for a Rule, we muſt conclude that this Tranſaction now before us, is God's doing, ſince the vaſt importance of it is ſo viſible, that it may be perhaps leſſened rather than aggravated, if one would attempt to ſet it forth. You all know what you both felt and feared: the overturning this Church, and the ſubverting of this Government, muſt in conſequence have brought on the Ruine both of the Proteſtant Religion and the publick Liberty all <hi>Europe</hi> over. When all this is ſtopp'd, and a happy <hi>Criſis</hi> appears, that gives the faireſt hopes not only of the ſecuring our Religion, together with our other Temporal Concerns, but of putting a check to the Spirit of Perſecution, which has of late raged ſo furiouſly againſt our Brethren in ſo many different places of <hi>Europe,</hi> and that the Perſecutor of Religion, and the Raviſher of Liberty, and the Scourge of the Age, after his having been ſo long a Plague to all his Neighbours, may probably be brought to feel a little of thoſe Miſeries which he has laid on others; ſo great a Tranſaction as this, which is perhaps the fore-runner of a greater, may upon very juſt grounds be called the Lord's doing, if every thing that is great is ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Things in which God's Honour is moſt particularly concerned, may be well reckoned his <hi>doing;</hi> for if he has a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that extends it ſelf to all Things, wee have much more Reaſon to conclude, that Mankind has a more ſpecial Title to it: And among Men, that Chriſtians are under a particular diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and of all Chriſtians, that thoſe who have reduced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44659:3"/>to its Primitive Purity and Simplicity, are its chief care; ſo that the reeſtabliſhing of that Glorious Work, which God in a ſeries of many ſignal Providences had ſet up in the laſt Age, and which for the Sins and the unreformed Practices of thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to it, was brought ſo low in this, may be juſtly aſcribed to that Sovereign Wiſdom that governs the Church, which was purchaſed by <hi>the Blood of the Son of GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Matters of Controverſy are not proper upon this Occaſion; but without entring far into them, the common ſenſe of Mankind, and the general Notices of Truth that are impreſſed upon our Minds, may ſerve to determine the greateſt part of the differences between us and our Perſecutors, Whether Men ought to ſatisfy themſelves in the Points of Religion, or ought to take them upon truſt? Whether Men ought to put the ſtreſs of their Religion upon a real Renovation of Heart and Life? or, if it may do full as well, to hire and pay a Prieſt for forgiving our ſins in this Life, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming us from the puniſhment of them in the next? Whether we ought to believe our Senſes and Reaſon in their proper Objects, or not? And not to run out too far, whether thoſe Eternal Rules of Juſtice and Mercy, ought to be the Meaſures of our Actions, or if Zeal for Holy Church, can warrant us to break our Faith, and deſtroy our Neighbours? All theſe ſeem to be ſo plain; that one would think the Deciſion ſhould be ſoon made; and indeed, if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that falſe ſhew of Learning, and the many hard words with which theſe Matters have been diſguiſed and intangled, Men would try them in a ſhorter and ſimpler Method, Truth would be ſooner found out. In a word; The Truth of our Religion appearing to us in ſo many conſpicuous Characters, eſpecially after the noble and worthy Endeavours of ſo many of the Lights of this Church, who have propoſed all the Points in diſpute to the World with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages beyond any thing that had appeared ever ſince the firſt beginnings of thoſe Conteſts. After all this, I ſay, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this <hi>is the Lord's doing;</hi> ſince a work that is ſo dear to him, ſeems now to be again received into his protection, in ſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal a manner, after he had ſeemed to hide himſelf from it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe Providences which ſeem immediately to work upon the Minds of Men, and to engage them into the Deſigns of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, are in a more conſpicuous manner the <hi>Work of God.</hi> For the Mind of Man being a free Agent, it is leſs accountable how vaſt Multitudes ſhould come all under the ſame Impreſſions, unleſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44659:4"/>God did by thoſe ſecret and undiſcernable Methods of his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, give them ſuch directions. This <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſeems to be penned upon the making up of that Breach that was between the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Saul;</hi> all <hi>Iſrael</hi> following the latter, while only the Tribe of <hi>Judab</hi> adhered to the former, ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. But all were afterwards united in owning of <hi>David,</hi> who was become the <hi>Head Stone of the Corner,</hi> that joined thoſe two great Diviſions in one. <hi>David</hi> had felt how little either <hi>Princes or People,</hi> that is, thoſe of the <hi>Sanhedrim;</hi> or to ſpeak in an Engliſh Phraſe, the <hi>Peers</hi> or <hi>Commons</hi> of the Jews, were to be depended upon: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9, and 10. he ſays, <hi>It is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put confidence in Man: It is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put confidence in Princes,</hi> either numerous Armies, or wiſe Councils. The Reign of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Charms that were in <hi>Jonathan,</hi> had, no doubt, given the family a great Root. But the Divine Deſignation that was upon <hi>David,</hi> had broke through all that, and had turned the the Hearts of the whole Nation as one Man to him. <hi>David</hi> had ſeen a formidable oppoſition in his way, and he himſelf had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through great and threatning Dangers; but the <hi>right Hand of the Lord</hi> had been of his ſide, and had done <hi>valiantly.</hi> And all the Force that was brought againſt him, had vaniſhed into nothing; or as a <hi>Fire of Thorns,</hi> it had blazed and crackled a little, but was ſoon ſpent: And therefore as there was an univerſal rejoicing in the <hi>Tabernacle of the Righteous,</hi> ſo <hi>David</hi> went into the Houſe of God, this Pſalm being ſet as the Hymn of his Triumph: which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably ſung before him as he went into the Tabernacle in Mount <hi>Zion;</hi> for theſe words, <hi>Open to me the gates of Righteouſneſs, I will go into them and praiſe the Lord,</hi> together with the Anſwer, <hi>This is the gate of the Lord into which the Righteous ſhall enter,</hi> ſeem to be ſet for his entring in at the Gates: In a word, the centring of the whole People in him, was ſo particularly a work of Providence, that in a moſt ſpecial manner <hi>this was the Lords doing.</hi> And therefore an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary concurrence of all favourable Accidents, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the diſpoſing of all Mens minds one way, has a Character upon it, that muſt force us to ſay, <hi>This is the Lords doing.</hi> I know how dangerous and deceitful an Argument this from Providence will ever ſeem to be; and therefore I will touch, it with that caution which is requiſite. It is certain, that God for the puniſhing of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, gives ſometimes ſuch a torrent of Succeſs to thoſe who are the Inſtruments of their Correction, that this may be rather a mark
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44659:4"/>of his diſpleaſure againſt thoſe who are to be brought low, than of his favouring thoſe who are lifted up. There are alſo ſuch Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the whole Conduct of the World, that though our Partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty makes us apt to Magnifie all that we like, yet if we carry it too far, we will be in danger to be often out of countenance, when the ſame Argument turn againſt us; therefore before we can make any Comments on ſo doubtful a Text, we muſt be firſt ſure that the ground work is well laid, and that both the Cauſe it ſelf, and the means uſed to advance it, are good. But when we are got over that, and are ſatisfied both in the one and the other, then we can hardly forbear to look on a chain of unlook'd for and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Providences, without a moſt ſenſible Joy. I will not build too much on the Characters that have appeared in the Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible part of the Creation, I mean the Winds and Weather, for one does not know how far thoſe have been the effects of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſeries of things, yet one croſs Wind which ſeemed deſign'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make us apprehend the hand of Heaven, without ſuffering much by it, and without loſing above one Man in it; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrong and proſperous Gale, which both preſerved us from thoſe who were appointed to wait for us, add brought us ſo near our Port, but changed immediately for another to fetch us into it; and which having executed its Commiſſion, was immediately in another corner, and the ſoftneſs of the Weather, in a Seaſon ſo far advanc'd, are things ſo remarkable, that we are extream inſenſible if they make not deep Impreſſions on us. But, as I ſaid before, the application of Providence in the turning and bending the minds of Men, is yet a moſt immediate work of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The precipitation and folly of Perſecutors in opening their ill deſigns ſo early, the Impudent breach of Faith, and the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting Cruelty that they had put in practice in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kingdom, ſent us over many thouſands of Witneſſes, to awaken us, and to let us ſee what we ought to look for whenſoever that bloody Religion ſhould come to prevail among us; and of what account all Promiſes and Laws were to be, whenſoever they could break through them. This comming ſo critically, in the very time in which the Repeal of Laws was to be asked in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, was a more ſenſible Argument againſt it, than all the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ones could ever be that were brought for it; and ſo much Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was neceſſary, otherwiſe the good Nature of ſome, and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44659:5"/>weakneſs and corruption of others, had perhaps put us to a more Melancholy and Troubleſome after game; but ſuch an apparent breach of Faith, and ſo furious a Perſecution as they had raiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, were Arguments that every Man could comprehend and manage, and out of which it was not poſſible to beat them. I need not enlarge on all that chain of Errors and Violences that have followed, ſince the firſt broaching of the Deſign; they were too many to be all repeated, and too viſible and well known to need that it ſhould be done. Nor would I willingly ſay any thing that might look either like Inſulting or Reproaching, God has ſeemed to have given them up to ſuch a Spirit of deluſion, as if the Curſe of thoſe who Worſhip graven Images, had fallen on them; <hi>Like unto them are all they that worſhip them:</hi> and in Concluſion, GOD put ſuch a Cup of <hi>trembling and aſtoniſhment in their hands,</hi> that he ſeemed to have taken away <hi>the heart of the Counſellors,</hi> and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to another of <hi>Davids</hi> Expreſions, <hi>none of the men of might have found their hands;</hi> in ſhort, the Methods that God has ſuffered them to take for the alarming and awakning the whole Nation, for the uniting of all that were ſo unhappily broken aſunder before, and for ingaging all to center in what is now brought about, is an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Character of the hand of God in the whole matter: Why went they ſo faſt and ſo barefac'd? Why graſp'd they ſo much all at once? Why was the Hook ſo ill covered when the Bait was thrown out? Why was it that few were either ſo weak or ſo corrupt, but they have been ſo ſucceſsful that they at laſt have ſet them right? In a word, all this blaſting of Counſels, and defeating of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns by their own means, was of God, and muſt be owned to be his doing.</p>
            <p>The Errors alſo of the great Supporter of Perſecution, his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels with the Head of that Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> and his diverting his Force to a new War, an unjuſt one, to be ſure, ſince begun by him; the Concurrence of ſo many great Princes, and above all that happy Union that was in thoſe Bleſſed Provinces, that tho' compos'd of ſo many different Bodies, ſeem'd to have but one Head and one Heart upon this Occaſion, are all conſpicuous Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters. The Conſtitution and the Intereſts of the States do always byaſs them againſt War, or every thing that may interrupt their Trade; and the Dangers which appeared from a War in their Frontier, ſeemed at leaſt to engage them to ſecure themſelves rather by a ſtrengthning than a diminiſhing of their Force; and yet the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44659:5"/>univerſal and chearful Concurrence of all among them, from the Higheſt to the Loweſt, both thoſe that were in the Government, and thoſe that were without doors, by which they put their whole Strength to this Deſign, and put all to hazard to carry it on, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring neither their Fleets, their Armies, nor their Treaſure; all this, I ſay, made every one conclude, that this was the Finger of God. The Concurrence of all in this Nation, &amp; eſpecially of that Great Body from which the chief Oppoſition was expected, was no leſs ſignal. Their Numbers, and that courage which is ſo natural to this noble Nation, and many other Conſiderations, concurred to give juſt Apprehenſions of a Bloody Scene. But how ſtrangely did all this vaniſh? And how have our Hopes and even our Wiſhes been ſo far prevented, that we are ſcarce yet recovered out of that ſurprize of Wonder into which this threw us? When all this is laid together, we are tempted not only to cry out, that this is the <hi>Lords doing,</hi> but that it is ſuch a doing of his as is beyond any thing that is in all the Records of paſt Times; and is a Scene all of Wonders, but Wonders of Love and Mercy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When Revolutions happen, that carry ſo many Characters of the Attributes of God on them, that we ſee both Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs in every Step of them, then we are yet more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly bound to adore the Hand of God in them. The Progreſs that <hi>Mahomet</hi> and his Followers made, which is indeed one of the moſt amazing things in Hiſtory, carried evident Marks of the Power end Juſtice of GOD, in ſuffering that Scourge of the Eaſtern Chriſtians to bring them under his cruel Yoke. The Progreſs of the <hi>Roman</hi> State had in it Characters both of the Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of GOD, in diſpoſing the World for the Chriſtian Religion, by bringing it under one Empire, and ſuch a Civilized Gorvern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as was a due Preparation for ſo holy and perfect Religion. But here we have both Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring to ſet forth the Glory of the Author of it. So great an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and the ſeveral Branches of it, all meeting ſo happily together, and favoured with ſo many proſperous Accidents, ſhew how the Power of GOD concurred in it. The Depth, the Secrecy, the prudent Management and Execution of it, ſhew the Wiſdom of GOD; but above all, the ſudden and unbloody Iſſue to which it was ſo unexpectedly brought, is a Character of GOD<hi>'S</hi> Goodneſs to us, which can never be ſufficiently acknowledged: If either a ſlow Lingering had made us languiſh, or a bloody Deciſion had
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44659:6"/>been the price of the Victory, we ſhould have had reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that, our Sins had rendred us unworthy of ſo great a Mercy as we haye now before us: But with how much admiration muſt we look on and ſee our ſelves prevented with ſo early a Deliverance? and that our Deliverer, as he came deteſting the Imputation of Conqueſt that was call on him, ſo he was received in a way ſuitable to his own good Intentions. And thus upon all theſe Reaſons, as we ſee in general what are the Characters from which we may conclude what things may be called the <hi>Lord's doing,</hi> ſo we ſee in particular how fitly they all belong to that which is the Subject of our wonder at preſent.</p>
            <p>For this <hi>is mavellous in our eyes.</hi> We talk of it, both to our ſelves, and to one another in this ſtyle: who can ceaſe wondring, eſpecially thoſe who have ſeen how the ſprings of this Affair have moved all along? We wonder at the Deliverance it ſelf, and we ought to wonder much more ſuch a Guilty Nation as this is, ſhould have been delivered in ſo harmleſs a manner. We ſee what a ſtorm has gone over, and broke out upon many of the For reign Churches. A Perſecution that is in all its Circumſtances far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the blackeſt of any that are in Hiſtory. If our Church has advantages in her Conſtitution, that make her the juſt pride and glory of the whole proteſtant Side; we have ſtill ſo much the more to anſwer for, if we have not walked worthy of thoſe Bleſſings, that Light, and thoſe Advantages with which God had honoured us. And why is it then that God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only only ſhaken the Rod over us, but has not ſuffered it to hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s? Our Enemies had rage enough to deſign it, and they had an abuſed Authority ſo entirely in their hands, that they ſeemed to have got the Government un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as implicit obedience, as they have got over the Faith of their Votaries. How comes it then that God did not ſuffer this to go farther, that he did not puniſh our ſins, and in particular the ſharpneſs with which we had treated one another, by delivering us up to thoſe whoſe tender mercies are cruel? All this is marvellous, but whether it is ſo in our eyes or not, I do not know: that is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we make thoſe Reflections on it, which ſuch miracles of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy call for from us; or if we let it paſs by us without any other Reflection but of talking about it, as we do concerning all other Revolutions: In a word, as this is the <hi>Lord's doings and marvellous in it ſelf,</hi> ſo it ought to be ſo <hi>in our eyes;</hi> for it is certainly in the the eyes of all the World beſide. We ought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44659:6"/>to make ſuch pauſes in thinking on it, as may lead us up to adore and admire the great Author of it, in this his doing.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt,</hi> We ought in a moſt profound proſtration, to magnify the good-of God to us in it: to him belongs the Glory of it, for his hand has wrought this Salvation for us. Some may mention their Chariots, and ſome their Horſes, but we ought only to mention the name of the Lord our God. It will not all derogate from the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Honour of our Great-Deliverer, to conſider him as the Inſtrument, whom God has ſo highly exalted, in bringing about ſo great a work by his means; and ſo to direct our Homage and Adoration to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of this, and all our other Bleſſings. And God has imployed an Inſtrument in it, who deſires that the acknowledgments may be wholly made to that Eternal Purpoſe, that brings abour all its Deſigns in ſo Sovereign a manner. This is indeed in all it parts above the skill and wiſdom of Man: and therefore let us offer up the whole honour of it to God: and when that is done, this will lead us beſt of all to pay all the due returns of gratitude and eſteem to Him whom God hath now bleſſed for the ſecond time with the greateſt honour that can fall on a mortal Man, that he ſeems born to be the great Bleſſing of the Age. His firſt appearance in the World carried with it a Deliverance to thoſe happy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Provinces; for happy they were, from the time that they came under His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. We that ſaw their Peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Plenty, and the Order and Juſtice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Reign among them, and the ſenſe that they have of that Conduct that procures, it ſaw an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of thoſe Bleſſings that ſeem to be before us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And indeed the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that they all expreſſed at His leaving them; was to us the trueſt Indication of the joy and confidence with which we ought to receive Him here, and of the hopes that we may promiſe our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo glorious a Protection. Let us therefore ponder all theſe Providences of God ſo as to admire them, not only into a lazy and ſilent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wonder, but in thoſe true acts of Praiſe and Adoration, by which <hi>our ſouls, and all that is within us, may he ſtirred up to bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs the Lord, and not to forget anyone of all thoſe benefits which he has beſtowed on us, upon this occaſion, in which he has redeemed our life from deſtruction, and crowned us with bis loving-kindneſs and tender meroies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> If this Work of God does poſſeſs us with that veneration which is due to it, we ought not to ſtop the courſe of it, till it has had its full effect; nor to daub matters by ſlight and palliating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. We ſee now before us the moſt glorious beginning of a noble Change of the whole face of Affairs, both with relation to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44659:7"/>Religion, and the Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> that we could have wiſht for It is ſo for beyond our hopes, that we durſt ſcarce let our wiſhes go ſo far: we may, it we are not wanting to put ſelves, and to the Conjuncture before us, hope to ſee that which may be according to the Prophetick ſtyle, termed <hi>a new Heaven's, and a new Earth.</hi> But if a Spirit of jealouſy and murmuring, of impatience and faction, and of returning back to that out of which God has ſo ſignally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricated us, grows up; ſo that inſtead of reaping the fruits that we have now in proſpect, we have not Souls big enough, nor Hearts good enough, to carry this on to perfection, then we may juſtly fear our being delivered up avail thoſe Evils from which we will not be healed. But it on the other hand we raiſe our minds above every narrowneſs of thought, and all partial regards, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der matters with ſuch a naked impartiality as becomes Chriſtians, Proreſtants and Engliſhmen, and provide ſuch Remedies as are requiſite, then we may hope to ſee this bleſſed morning to grow up to a perfect day. In a word, <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> are before us, and <hi>Bleſſing</hi> and <hi>Curſing.</hi> Thoſe who chuſe <hi>Life,</hi> and every thing that leads to it, ſecure a Bleſſing to themſelves, and entail it on their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: but if we chuſe <hi>Death</hi> rather than <hi>Life,</hi> there is no help for it: ſuch perſons ſecure a curſe to themſelves, and do what in them lies to entail it on their Poſterity; and there is ſcarce any indicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more certain of the Sins of a Nation being grown up to that height, that it muſt be deſtroyed, than the Miſcarriage of ſo great a Deliverance is God has wrought for us, which will be an eternal Blot on the Wiſdom of the Nation; ſince, in that Caſe the Figure of our Saviour muſt be juſtly applyed to us: <hi>We have piped to you, but you have not danced;</hi> or theſe other words of his, <hi>O Jeruſalem, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, how often would I have gathered thee under my wings, at the hen gathereth her brood, hut thou wouldeſt not:</hi> Or that of the Prophet, That while <hi>Children were in the Womb, there was not ſtrength to bring forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly,</hi> But if we will carry on, and perfect this marvellous Work of GOD, we muſt ſtudy to be ſuch, that GOD may not repent him of the good which he ſeems to have prepared for us. While we are under ſuch a happy Influence of Heaven, we muſt not raiſe up ſuch an Interpoſition between it and us, as may not only make us loſe this happy Opportunity, but turn it to a Curſe by the ill uſe we may make of it. We have not forgot the Criminal Exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the year Sixty, and how that great Revolution that ſeemed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44659:7"/>to promiſe all that a Nation that had been ſo long toſſed with Wars and changes of Government, could wiſh for, was ſo unſucceſsful; but inſtead of the Nations receiving that with thoſe Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that were due for ſuch a Bleſſing; how did all People, as it were, conſpire to defeat the ends of Providence in it? The exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Rioting and Drunkenneſs, and the Diſorders of all ſorts, grew not only to be practiſed, but gloried in, as if thoſe Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations had been the proper diſtinctions of a Loyal man; a Virtuous man looked out of Countenance, if he could not go in to the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the time; and becauſe the high Profeſſions of Religion in the former times, had been a diſguiſe to many ill Deſigns, men not only laid aſide all the Decencies of Religion, but began to think it a peece of breeding to decry it as an Impoſture. This went ſo far, that perhaps in no Nation, under Heaven, did men treat the Religion which they profeſſed, ſo familiarly as we did; and thoſe who were not concerned any further in Religion, than as it might advance their ungodly Deſigns, were willing to encourage this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Atheiſm, hoping that it would make way for a Religion which in ſome reſpects is worſe than no <hi>Religion</hi> at all; for tho, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationto particular Men, there is no Compariſon indeed to be made between <hi>Popery &amp; Atheiſm;</hi> yet, with relation to <hi>humane Society,</hi> a <hi>Religion</hi> that diſſolves Faith and good Nature, and gives Authority both to Perfidy and Cruelty, is worſe than none at all. As we reflict upon theſe Abominations, and on the fatal Conſequences of them, which have been on us ſo long; ſo in order to the preventing the return of the like Evils, we muſt avoid the relapſing into the like Sins. It is neither the Union nor Wiſdom of Councils, nor the Strength of Fleets or Armies, that will ſecure us from the Judgements of God, which we may expect will fall upon us with an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary redoubling, according to the Prophetick Phraiſe of ſeven times heavier than any thing that we have yet ſeen or known; <hi>if thoſe that are filthy, will be filthy ſtill:</hi> If the Atheiſt will think that his ſtanding up for the Proteſtant Religion, is a warrant to him to laugh at all that is Sacred; In a word, if Men think that their Fears are over; that, therefore they may give themſelves up to work wickedneſs without reſtraint; then we may juſtly expect a return of the like; if not of greater Miſeries. We deſpiſed our Religion, and GOD has threatned to take it from us; yet it ſeems the Prayers of the Few have prevailed over the cry of the ſins of the many. But we have no reaſon to expect that it ſhould be always
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44659:8"/>ſo. We are certainly the happieſt Nation in the World, if we can but know and value it as we ought to do. Our Climate, through none of the beſt, yet is Kind and Fruitful: and if the Sun is leſs favourable to us; yet our Situation as it ſeparates us from all the World, ſo it lets the Wealth of the whole World in upon us, and keeps Danger and War at a diſtance from us: We have all the Liberties of Freemen tempered with a firm and ſteady Government. But which is above all, we are bleſt with that holy Religion which the Son of God revealed to the World, and we are Reformed from thoſe Corruptions which had defiled it, and that in ſo equal manner, that we are the chief Object of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Fury, as well as the juſt Glory of the Reformation: We have had the truths of Religion both in the points of Speculation and Practice opened to us with ſuch advantages, that if we ſtumble or loſe our way in the midſt of ſo much light, we have more to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for than any Nation under Heaven: and to Crown all, God his put us ſo far into the hands of our Enemies, as to let us clearly ſee what we were to expect from them. They had devoured us in their hopes, and ſeemed; to be <hi>Haman's</hi> Friends calling Lots, and watching a fit opportunity to deſtroy us, when of a ſudden the Snare was broken, and we have eſcaped out of it. I hope none of thoſe that were here well ſoon or eaſily forget how near they were to be ſwallowed up; and if they had then grave thoughts and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious purpoſes, I hope this change in their Fortunes will not make them diſmiſs, or forget them, And for us, that ſaw God's Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Deep, and that after we had paſt an Eminent Danger, languiſhed ſo many dayes in the Harbour between Hope and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, upon which we ſeemed to put on firm reſolutions, and make ſolemn Vows of amendment, Can we be guilty of ſo hainous an Ingratitude and breach of Faith; as to forget the engagem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts, into which we then entred, of a ſerious and univerſal Reformation?</p>
            <p n="4">4. But while we let our thoughts out to wonder at the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, let the admiration of theſe produce ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like them in our ſelves: we ought to grow wiſe; for our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience has coſt us dear, and had almoſt proven a very dreadful School to us: We now ſee the folly of truſting to that Religion, and of imagining that any weight was to be laid on all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that could be made us by them. It is not to be doubted but that many were ſo little acquainted with the depths of Satan that are in that Black Society, as to believe it was poſſible for them to maintain Truth, Honour and Good nature; notwithſtanding the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44659:8"/>points of Speculation that are in their Schools: we reſolved to make the Experiment, and they have taken ſuch pains to let us ſee our miſtake, that it is to be hoped will never at any time hereafter relapſe into the like Error. The goodneſs of God, that appears now in ſuch endearing Characters to us, ought likewiſe to form the like temper in us. Our minds have been to much em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bittered on all hands, by reaſon of ſome inconſiderable differences which our Enemies have always managed, with ſo much addreſs, as to engage us to weaken our common Force, by dividing our ſelves into Parties: and by a fatal ſerie of woful Accidents, theſe ſparks have been blown up into ſuch a flame, that they had almoſt quite conſumed us. But it is to be hoped that we will ſtudy to be all of one mind; or, if we cannot arrive at ſo great. bleſſing, that at leaſt we will love one another, and remember that we are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, fellow Chriſtians and fellow Proteſtants, that muſt have been deſtroyed together, and therefore muſt now ſupport and bear with one another. But as I doubt not but the happy diſpoſition of all peoples minds will now produce a deſired temper in thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; ſo we muſt not bound out Charity within ſo narrow a compaſs: No, we are Chriſtians, and therefore we muſt not only love our Brethren, but even our Enemies and our Perſecutors, and ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their evil with good. For how hard thoughts, ſoever we may juſtly have of the Spirit and Councils that govern that that Church; yet many among them in the ſimplicity of their heart, and according to the impliciteneſs of the Principles follow thoſe Opinions that have been dropt into them from their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; they have not ſtrength of thought to look narrowly into them; nor do their Rules allow them in ſo bold a thing as to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether they are in the right or not: and though it is hard to imagine how any ſhould go over to them; yet it is eaſie to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine how theſe who are among them ſhould be ſhut up blindfold &amp; muffled up with the awful bonds of <hi>Authority</hi> &amp; <hi>Infallibility.</hi> And for ſuch, though we are under the higheſt provocations that any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can have; yet after all, let us ſtill remember that we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and that as we have declared openly againſt the Injuſtice and Cruelty of our Enemies, we govern our ſelves by the Rule of doing as we would be done by. It is a preſage of Moderation in our whole proceedings, that even the leſs governable Part of the Nation, I mean the unruly Multitude, has been ſo happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from extravagant acts of fury: for without juſtifying what they have done, we may well rejoyce for what they have not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44659:9"/>done, and that Bloody and Outragious Sacrifices have not been made. It is the peculiar Character and Glory of this Nation, That Tenderneſs and Compaſſion are ſo natural to it, that the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate are always pitied by them. And if tumultuous Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have obſerved ſo much temper in their wrath, how much more is to be expected from Councils that are to be governed by Juſtice and Mercy, and under the directions of a Prince who has ſhewed that his hatred of Perſecution in others, was not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own ſide ſuffered in it; but from a ſteadly and uniform Principle which has made him not only juſt to thoſe of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but even kind too, whenſoever they deſerved it. We, indeed, ought to ſtudy the firm ſecuring of our Religion, even from the remoteſt poſſibilities of hurt that can come to it from that reſtleſs and violent ſpirit which has hithero created us ſo much trouble; this we owe to Almighty God, to this Glorious Church, to our Selves &amp; to our Poſterity: but in doing this we muſt ſo govern our ſelves, as not to ſuffer our Blood to boil too high, nor our Thoughts to run too faſt; and while we conſider that we may perhaps owe our Enemies, we ought to take care not to forget what we owe our ſelves, that ſo we may look to the honour, as well as the ſecurity of our Holy Religion. In a word, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to be Chriſtians indeed, and to act as Men that have thoſe undefiled Rules, and that bright Example, which our Saviour has given us. ever in our Eyes, and then it is impoſſible for us to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry. But if Revenge and Animoſity prevail over the ſofter and wiſer Councils, that Reaſon and Religion may ſuggeſt, and if in all that we do, we take not care to have God ever on our ſides, it will be eaſie for him to blaſt all Councils, and to defeat even the greateſt and beſt laid Deſigns. We have now before our Eyes, one of the ſignalleſt Inſtances that is in any Hiſtory, of the Inſtability of all human things: on which one cannot refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct without making a full ſtop in his thoughts. But the ſubject is ſo ſpeaking, that it needs not be inſiſted on, and there are particular Circumſtances in it that forbid it; but if it is not decent to ſpeak much of it, yet I hope none are ſo inſenſible as not to think much of it. Perhaps ſome may imagine that are ſafe, becauſe we cannot be daſhed on the ſame Rock about which we ſee ſo great a Shipwarck; but alas, if we provoke God to hide his Face, and to withdraw his Protection from us, his ways are paſt finding out, he can bring ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction on us from that hand from which we perhaps apprehend on us from that hand from which we perhaps apprehend it the leaſt: If Proſperity and Succeſs blow and up, and make them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44659:9"/>forget God and all the Vows that they made to him, he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want means and methods to make them return to themſelves, and to remember him.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter then, ſince God has wrought ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary a deliverance for us; let us adore him, who is the true Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it; and under him let us pay all the returns poſſible of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Gratitude to that Bleſſed Inſtrument on whom he has laid ſo much Glory. Let us improve it to the higheſt and nobleſt ends that can be thought on; let us live under as becomes thoſe who take care to do nothing that may render them unworthy of the continuance of it: and let us all, in our ſeveral Stations, ſtudy to behave our ſelves ſo, That the Glory as well as the Safety of the Nation, and the luſtre as well as the eſtabliſhment of our Religion; may be raiſed up to that pitch, that the Name of an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> and a Proteſtant may have a ſound all the World over, that may give Terror as well as creat Eſteem; and that this Work, which is now brought to ſo great a forwardneſs, may in due time attain to its full perfection; and that then we may all have reaſon to break forth in the Triumphant words with which this <hi>Pſalm</hi> begins; <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good, becauſe his mercy endureth for ever Let Iſrael now ſay, That his mercy endureth for ever. Let the houſe of Aaron now ſay, That his mercy endureth for ever. And let them that fear the Lord ſay, That bis mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
